A Guide to the Papers of the Mount Crawford Division of the Virginia Sons of Temperance, 1815-1892 (bulk 1846-1892)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Mount Crawford Division of the Virginia Sons of Temperance 1815-1892 (bulk 1846-1892)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1014
This collection consists of 50 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on 1940 December 1.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of the Sons of Temperance include minutes, 1848-1857; account books of dues, 1849-1868, 1873-1888; rosters of members suspended or expelled, 1840-1860, 1866; list of associate members, 1878-1887; a name index, n.d.; a list of members who pledged total abstinence, 1876-1888; and miscellaneous material including receipts, songs, a thesis on pneumonia, 1869, for the Medical College of Virginia faculty by E.C. Staller, and a blacksmith's account book, 1815-1826.
Contents List
- Papers
  - Sons of Temperance: society business, miscellaneous. Includes ritual songs for meetings, receipts, and a thesis on pneumonia prepared for the faculty of the Medical College of Virginia in 1869 by E.C. Staller 1848-1892, n.d., 37 items. (Box 1)
- Bound Volumes
  - Account book of blacksmith Gabriel Stickley (1815-1826). Includes letter (1814) from a Rabaiah Stickley of Shenandoah County to his unnamed brother-in-law concerning military service 1815-1826 (Box 1)
  - Account book of general activities, purchases of produce, daily labor (1849-1853, 1874). Laid in the volume are two exercise books ascribed to a William Marshall, from his school days and beyond (1819, 1825-1855) 1819-1855 (Box 1)
  - "Alphabet of Divisions." Rosters of members expelled or suspended with date of action, name, and occupation from the Mount Crawford, Marshall, Valley, Rockingham, and Fountain Divisions 1846-1860 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of meetings, Mount Crawford Division. Appended are a list of divisions in Rockingham County, list of corresponding divisions elsewhere in the Shenandoah Valley, and a list of eligible officers 1848-1856 (Box 1)
  - Account book of dues received from the Mount Crawford Division 1849-1853 (Box 2)
  - Account book of dues received 1853-1868 (Box 2)
  - Records of Degree Division No. 19, Mount Crawford. Minutes of meetings (1855-1857); list of persons expelled (1866); list of associate members (1878-1882) 1855-1882 (Box 2)
  - Account book of dues received 1873-1874 (Box 2)
  - Account book presumably of a blacksmith 1876-1884 (Box 2)
  - Lists of associates, mostly women, a few boys, a rare man 1882-1887 (Box 2)
  - Index of names n.d. (Box 2)
  - Account book of dues paid and owed by members. Includes list (1876-1888) of members who had taken pledges of total abstinence, with name, and often age, occupation and address 1874-1888